Oh my goodness. It is time at long last
to talk about the American Revolution,
baby. So, excuse me while I high five a
bald eagle. Oh, that felt good. All
right, if you're ready to get them brain
cows milked Revolution style, then let's
get to it. So, let me begin by stating
what may not be obvious. Namely, that on
paper, the American should not have won
this war against the British. Like, this
was not David versus Goliath. This was
more like the flee in David's hair
against Goliath. And the British Goliath
had two massive advantages. First, Great
Britain had developed arguably the most
powerful military in the world after
amassing such a large maritime empire,
especially their naval power. Not to
mention, they had plenty of practice
killing other armies, what with their
almost constant wars with France and
other European powers. Additionally, the
British army was about 50,000 strong.
And in order to fight this war, the
British hired German soldiers known as
Hessins to fight with them to the tune
of about 30,000. And in addition to all
of that, they had long-standing
alliances with various American Indian
groups. All of which swelled their ranks
to numbers that greatly overwhelmed the
untrained ragtag American patriot
militias. Like I said, on paper, the
math is mathing all the way in favor of
a British victory. But then the second
advantage on the British side of the
ledger was the significant loyalist
opposition in the colonies. So the best
estimates say that no more than half of
the population in the colonies supported
the patriot cause for independence. like
it was very much not the case that all
the colonists in North America were
stoked about a war of independence
against Great Britain. No, hopefully
you'll recall from previous videos that
for a long time most of the colonists
wanted to remain British subjects but
they just wanted their full rights as
such. And so by the time of the
revolution a significant number of those
people still wanted to remain loyal to
Great Britain, which is why they were
called loyalists. And by significant
number, I mean 15 to 20% of the
population were loyalists who opposed
the revolution and wanted to remain
loyal to Britain. And those loyalists
were made up of various socio-economic
groups. A large percentage of the
loyalists were elite folks who had
gained much wealth and land and
therefore wanted no part in a revolution
that might threaten the system that had
made them rich. However, there were also
many common folks that remained
loyalists because they resented the
elite patriots who dominated affairs in
their region and had marginalized the
interest of the lower class. So yeah,
those two realities presented
significant obstacles to the patriot
cause in the American Revolution. And
before I tell you how they overcame
those obstacles, let me just say that
you two might be feeling like a flea in
David's hair against the Goliath of this
a push course. You know I got you, boo.
Behold my a pushheimler review guide
which has everything you need to study
for your unit exams and that beast of a
national exam as fast as possible. So if
that's something you're into, then get
that clicky finger out and check the
link in the description. Okay. Now,
despite all those obstacles working
against the colonial patriots, I hope
it's not a spoiler to let you know
upfront that the American patriots won
the war. Now, excuse me while I ch bump
the Declaration of Independence.
Okay, now that I've sufficiently
demonstrated my patriotism, let me give
you a piece of bad news. This is not
strictly a video about the history of
the American Revolution. This is a
curriculum video for the A push course
and that means that I'm leaving out most
of the juicy bits that Americans have
come to cherish and I'm focusing only on
what you need to know for your exam. But
to assuage any potential disappointment,
behold once again my patriotism. Okay,
now there are essentially four factors
that contributed to the American victory
that you're going to need to know. The
first factor includes the actions of
colonial militias and the Continental
Army. Now, the Continental Army was
formed by the Second Continental
Congress in response to British
aggression at Lexington and Conquer. And
prior to this creation of a national
army, each colony could muster their own
militia in order to respond to a crisis.
But this was the first time an army was
formed to represent all the colonies.
Even so, these American soldiers were in
general poorly equipped, poorly trained,
and often deserted their ranks.
Therefore, in the first 6 months of the
war, the Continental Army never won a
single victory in battle, and it
appeared that the overwhelming forces of
the British would prevail. And I know I
said their actions were a factor in the
American victory and at this point it
very much sounds like the American army
was about as effective as a woodpecker
with rubber lips. But stick with me cuz
it's going to get better. Anyway, the
second factor was the leadership of
George Washington. A very insightful
move. The Continental Congress appointed
Washington as the general of the
Continental Army. And though he was
endlessly frustrated at the lack of
discipline in his troops, he was able to
achieve some strategic victories that
helped turn the tide. Case in point, the
Battle of Trenton in 1777. So in the
winter of that year, the British General
William How followed the long wartime
tradition of suspending military action
during the coldest months. Cuz you know,
nobody likes to shoot and kill other
human beings with cold fingies. Anyway,
hearing that House Hessen troops were
camped in Trenton, New Jersey,
weathering the ice and rain, Washington
seized the opportunity. On Christmas
Day, Washington led a contingent of
American troops across the river and
sprung a surprise attack on the Hessen
camp, scoring an easy victory. And the
historical record actually preserved
General Washington's own words upon that
victory. Merry Christmas. Y'all just got
Washington. Ho ho ho. Anyway, from
there, Washington led the army to
Princeton, New Jersey, and scored
another victory. And to be clear, these
were not major strategic wins and would
ultimately play very little role in the
American victory, but they were of huge
importance to the patriot morale and
proved that the British could be
defeated even with cold fingers. Anyway,
after this battle, Washington made camp
in Valley Forge for 6 months. And during
this time, he enlisted a Prussian
military drill boss named Friedrich von
Stuben. During those six months, von
Stuben worked tirelessly to whip
Washington soldiers into shape and help
them learn and enact the military
discipline that they sorely lacked. And
in the end, it worked pretty well, which
was a big morale boost for the troops.
Okay. Now, the third factor in the
American victory was the alliance with
France. You see, to leaders in the
Patriot cause, it was a given that they
needed French help to defeat the
British. And to that end, the
Continental Congress had sent Benjamin
Franklin to France late in 1776 in order
to secure the alliance. And look, they
were pretty confident that France would
agree to this because, as you may
recall, France and Britain were ancient
enemies. And here was an opportunity to
French slap the stupid British. But for
over a year, France would not commit to
the patriot cause. And why says you?
Well, says I, because the Americans
hadn't really shown sufficient signs
that victory was possible. But all that
changed in 1777. In the fall of that
year, patriot militias won a victory
against British forces at the Battle of
Saratoga in New York. And not just a
victory, like a resounding and decisive
victory. The British lost almost twice
as many soldiers as did the Patriots.
And when the British returned to take
Saratoga, the Patriots beat them yet
again, leading to the British surrender
of the town. So after that, Franklin was
able to secure the French alliance.
French troops were quickly dispatched to
reinforce the Continental Army with the
promise that Americans would help defend
France's Caribbean territories. And then
about a year later, Spain joined France
in support of the Patriot Cause in order
to protect their North American
territory. Okay. Now, the fourth cause
for the American victory was the
colonist ideological commitment and
resilience. Remember what I said in the
last two videos, namely that the
colonial mind was a wash in ideas like
liberty and independence and natural
rights and all the rest. And when the
fighting got tough and the war dragged
on and on, a commitment to those ideas
helped sustain them. I mean, think about
it. Great Britain was fighting to keep
economic and political control of an
empire. Woof. But the patriots believe
they were fighting for liberty and
freedom from tyranny. And so, it's not
hard to imagine which motive was more
inspiring to people on the battlefield
than all the people at home supporting
the cause. Like Thomas Payne's words and
common sense inflamed this desire for
liberty, saying that by emerging
victorious in this conflict, the
Americans have it in our power to begin
the world again. And oh, what a
tantalizing prospect that is. And that
idea was repeated in sermons and
pamphlets and articles spread throughout
the colonies arguing that America was
the one place on earth that true liberty
and freedom could take root. And thus,
their victory in the struggle was of
existential importance. If you put those
four factors in a pot, then baby, you
got a stew going. And that stew tastes
like an American victory in the
Revolutionary War. And here's how it
happened. So, seeking to crush the
patriot opposition in the south, the
British occupied Yorktown in Virginia
and waited for reinforcements to arrive
from New York. And then Washington along
with French generals the Marque de
Lafayette and K de Roshambo cut off the
British reinforcements and eventually
forced their surrender. And so it was
that the Battle of Yorktown in 1781
proved to be the final victory for the
patriots. Now the war was officially
ended with the signing of the Treaty of
Paris in 1783. And this document did
several important things. First, it, you
know, ended the war. But second, and
perhaps more significant, the Treaty of
Paris essentially doubled the land
holdings of the freshly born United
States. They got everything south of
Canada, north of Louisiana and Florida,
and all the way to the Mississippi
River. And all of that meant that the
war had been won and now it was time to
see if they really could begin the world
again. And spoiler alert, they
definitely began something, but it
wasn't nearly as romantic as all of
that. But I'm going to save that story
for the next video. Okay, click here to
watch my other unit 3 videos. And here's
my A push Himler review guide, which is
going to help you get an A in your class
and a five on your exam in May. I
appreciate you coming around and I'll
catch you on the flipflop. I'm lar.